Welcome to this deep dive.
Imagine spending, you know, 33 years of your
life mentoring someone, pouring every ounce of your
knowledge into them, only to ask them what
they've actually learned, and hear them say they
got exactly eight things out of it.
In Ayyuhal Walad Imam al-Ghazali's famous letter
to a former student, this very scenario is
the single most quoted vignette in the entire
text.
As part of our five-part series on
this letter, we're going to explore what those
eight things are, and confront the central question
of why these eight might just be enough
to carry a person through this life into
the next.
Yeah, the individuals involved in this exchange really
make the stakes incredibly high.
Oh, for sure.
Who exactly are we looking at here?
Well, we're looking at a conversation between Shaqiq
al-Balki, who was a revered spiritual master
in 8th century Khorasan, and his longtime student,
Hatim bin Ism Al-Assam.
And Ghazali actually pauses the broader theological argument
of his letter just to drop this story
right in the middle, doesn't he?
He does.
He is basically signaling to the reader that
this specific interaction contains a really unique, concentrated
form of certainty.
Okay, let's unpack this, because the scene itself
carries just immense emotional weight.
It really does.
Shaqiq looks at his student after decades of
companionship, and asks a very natural question about
the fruit of all that labor.
And Hatim just calmly replies that he has
obtained eight benefits.
Right.
And Shaqiq reacts like a parent who has
just been handed a tragic diagnosis.
He recites the Quranic verse that's reserved for
moments of profound grief.
The indeed to Allah we belong and to
him we shall return verse.
Exactly.
He is lamenting that his entire life's work
as a teacher has resulted in a mere
eight takeaways.
The tension in that moment is palpable.
Shaqiq feels a devastating sense of failure.
But Hatim remains entirely unbothered, right?
Like, he doesn't panic at all.
Completely unbothered.
He tells his teacher that this is the
absolute truth, and more importantly, he does not
need anything more.
He claims these eight are sufficient.
And I think we need to let that
tension hang in the air for you, the
listener, to decide as we proceed, who is
actually right here?
Is the heartbroken teacher who expected an encyclopedia
right?
Or is the serene student who found a
compass right?
Well, Shaqiq ultimately asks him to explain these
eight benefits.
And what emerges is a very specific methodology.
And the methodology is what makes it so
fascinating to me.
Because Hatim didn't just, you know, write down
eight quotes from a lecture.
No, not at all.
He developed an algorithm.
It's like a scientific method for the soul.
And he applied it eight distinct times.
That's a great way to put it.
He observes a human behavior, notices that the
things people value inevitably fail them, finds a
Quranic verse that offers the eternal alternative, and
then completely reorganizes his life around that verse.
So the structure itself is a method.
It's not a sermon.
Exactly.
And that pattern is the true inheritance he
received from his teacher.
The 33 years were not spent memorizing trivia.
They were spent mastering this interior pattern.
So how does he apply it first?
He applies it to the concept of devotion.
He looks at humanity and observes that everyone
has a beloved.
People pour their energy into spouses, children, friends,
wealth, or status.
Right.
But he notices a brutal expiration date attached
to all of them.
Yes.
Some of these beloveds abandon you when you
fall ill.
Some leave when you die.
Even the most fiercely loyal beloved will only
accompany you to the edge of the grave.
And once the earth is moved, every single
one of those companions goes home.
They do.
They turn their backs on the grave.
So Hatim realizes that if you are going
to invest your entire capacity for love into
something, it makes zero sense to choose a
beloved who refuses to cross the border with
you.
Precisely.
He concludes that the only companion that actually
goes into the grave, stays there, and illuminates
the dark is his collection of good deeds.
So he decides to make his actions his
actual beloved.
He does.
He elevates good deeds from a chore to
an object of genuine affection.
He treats them with the care and attention
that a person normally reserves for a spouse
or a child.
It's kind of like, um, imagine packing a
massive suitcase for a trip, right?
You pack all your favorite clothes, your gadgets,
everything.
And then you get to the airport and
Customs tells you they are confiscating absolutely everything
in the bag except the actions you took
before arriving.
It just shifts your entire focus.
That is a perfect analogy.
And this mirrors a foundational architecture laid out
by the Prophet Muhammad.
He taught that when a person dies, their
actions come to an end, except for three
things.
Which are?
A continuing charity, a knowledge from which benefit
is gained, and a pious child who prays
for them.
The through line here is that the only
things that survive you are the actions you
set in motion while you were alive.
Wow.
So transitioning from who we love in the
external world to who we listen to internally,
Hatim applies his method to our psychological appetites
next.
Right.
He looks at society and sees people entirely
enslaved to the demands of their lower soul,
what the Sufi tradition calls the nafs.
The nafs.
That's that base drive for immediate gratification.
The voice that demands pleasure and comfort regardless
of the long-term cost.
Yes.
And Hatim sees people following this voice while
genuinely believing they are exercising free will.
The tragedy of the lower soul is its
disguise.
It masquerades as your own personality.
That is terrifying.
So what verse does he anchor this second
benefit on?
He finds his anchor in a specific promise.
And I will quote the Yusuf Ali translation
here as it captures the gravity perfectly.
And for such as had entertained the fear
of standing before their Lord's tribunal and had
restrained their soul from lower desires, their abode
will be the garden.
So Hatim responds to this by establishing an
uncompromising blockade against his own appetites.
He does.
He states that he refused to fulfill any
of its desires until it surrendered and found
peace in worship.
He basically established a literal front against his
nafs.
OK, I have to name this because this
is a deeply uncomfortable concept for a modern
ear.
I completely agree.
We live in an era defined by accommodating
our internal desires.
We call it self-care or speaking our
truth.
The idea of looking at your own internal
wants and starving them of yeses sounds like
psychological torture to most people.
It does sound harsh.
Because we are conditioned to negotiate with ourselves.
Yeah.
We promise to eat healthy all week so
we can binge on the weekend.
But Hatim refuses to negotiate at all.
Well, the framework Hatim operates within recognizes that
you cannot negotiate with a fire.
Giving the lower soul a little bit of
what it wants does not pacify it.
It merely fuels it.
That makes a lot of sense.
Imam Ali articulated the danger of this internal
dynamic when he warned not to let the
lower soul be a partner in your decisions.
He pointed out that because the lower soul
speaks in your own voice, you will not
even notice its arguments.
So any compromise is just a trap.
You have to silence that internal negotiator to
hear anything else.
So once that internal noise is silenced, your
perspective on external society has to completely shift.
Because you aren't driven by those appetites anymore,
so you naturally start questioning the scoreboards people
use to measure the successful life.
Which brings us to the third benefit.
Hatim observes the sheer exhaustion of people hoarding
mortal possessions.
They sacrifice their time, their health, and their
ethics to build a pile of wealth.
Only to leave it behind for someone else
to spend.
Yes.
So he counters this exhausting pursuit with the
Quranic verse, what is with you must vanish,
what is with Allah will endure.
That is a stark reality check.
So his pivot there is absolute.
He decides that any wealth he accumulates should
be deposited where it cannot vanish.
Right.
He gives his wealth to the destitute, essentially
depositing it with God.
He transfers his assets out of this mortal
economy and into the eternal one.
And there's a prophetic tradition about this too,
right?
There is.
The prophet taught that your wealth is only
what you ate, what you wore, and what
you gave in charity to go ahead of
you.
It's literally like winning millions of chips at
a casino right before management kicks you out
and tells you the chips are worthless outside
the building.
The only way to keep the value is
to cash them out before you leave.
That is exactly it.
And for his fourth benefit, Hatim realizes the
same thing about societal status.
He watches people desperately trying to prove their
worth through these false scoreboards for grandeur.
He sees them relying on the size of
their tribe, the aggression they can display, or
the sheer amount of resources they can waste.
So how does he dismantle those false metrics?
By anchoring his life on this verse.
Verily, the most honored of you in the
sight of Allah is he who is the
most righteous of you.
The Quranic term there is taqwa.
Yeah.
A deep, watchful awareness of God's presence.
Yes.
Taqwa is the only valid metric of honor.
It is not about bloodlines, bank accounts, or
public displays of power.
It is an entirely private, internal state of
reverence.
So what does this all mean?
The psychological relief of dropping society's scoreboard is
immense.
Think about the energy you and I spend
worrying about our job titles, our zip codes,
or how we are perceived by people we
don't even like.
It is an exhausting way to live.
It really is.
Hatim looks at that entire game, realizes the
rules are completely made up, and simply walks
off the field.
And this connects across time.
His Highness Aga Khan IV spoke to this
exact paradigm when he noted that knowledge is
honored not for the diplomas on a wall,
but for what it makes a person actually
do.
And Imam Ali mirrored this as well, stating
that honor lies in the heart, not in
position.
Now, walking off that field naturally alters how
you view the people who are still playing
the game.
This brings us to Hatim's fifth observation.
If you drop the scoreboard, you stop being
jealous of your neighbor.
Precisely.
He watches humanity tearing itself apart through envy.
People complain, harbor bitterness, and sabotage each other
out of jealousy over possessions, status, and knowledge.
So he implies his method and finds the
next verse.
He finds the verse, It is we who
portion out between them their livelihood in the
life of this world.
Okay, this concept of pre-distribution creates serious
psychological friction.
The verse states that the division of resources
was decided long before we were even born.
Right, and from a practical standpoint, the realization
is that harboring malice toward your co-worker
for getting a promotion is entirely illogical.
Because your anger does not change the distribution.
Competing changes nothing.
But actually silencing that very human pang of
jealousy in real time is incredibly difficult.
The discipline required there is profound.
Hatim's solution is to stop holding grudges entirely.
Because he recognizes the source of the distribution,
he allows others to have their given share
without resentment.
And the Prophet offered a highly practical mechanism
for this too, didn't he?
He did.
He advised people to look at those who
are below them and to purposefully avoid looking
at those who are above them.
Because by controlling where you direct your attention,
you protect yourself from belittling the blessings you
have already been given.
It's not about complacency.
No, not at all.
It is a deliberate refusal to look sideways
at the runner next to you.
You realize you are not in a race
against them.
You are simply navigating the specific unique route
you are assigned.
And if your neighbor is not your rival,
it forces you to figure out who the
actual enemy is.
This is his sixth benefit.
He looks around and sees people consumed by
hatred for other human beings.
They spend their lives plotting against their peers.
Right, so he resolves this confusion by returning
to the text.
He finds the verse, Verily Satan is an
enemy to you, so treat him as an
enemy.
Hatim takes this directive literally.
If God explicitly names Satan as the open
enemy, then no human being can be the
ultimate enemy.
That is the core realization.
The person who wronged you is not the
true adversary.
The true adversary is the invisible mechanism of
division itself, the impulse that urges you to
hate another person.
By treating Satan as his sole enemy, he
frees himself from the exhausting burden of human
animosity.
Okay, but here's where it gets really interesting.
How so?
This leads to a very grounded practical problem
for his seventh benefit.
If you aren't competing with your neighbors and
you aren't hoarding wealth, how do you actually
survive in the physical world?
Well, Hatim watches people debase themselves, violate their
own ethics, and panic endlessly just to secure
their basic livelihood.
They take jobs that compromise their soul because
they're terrified of starving.
And that panic over sustenance is a universal
human condition.
But Hatim cures this panic with the verse,
There is no moving creature on earth, but
its sustenance dependeth on Allah.
He acknowledges that he is a moving creature
on earth, which means his sustenance is a
guaranteed responsibility of the divine.
Exactly.
He refuses to humiliate himself or violate his
principles out of economic terror.
But I have to play devil's advocate here.
The cynical interpretation of this is the couch
potato defense.
People hear that their sustenance is guaranteed and
assume they can just sit in their living
room and wait for a roasted chicken to
fall through the ceiling.
I want to clarify this carefully because Hatim
is not advocating for idleness.
He is not saying to do nothing.
Right.
He is saying, do not violate the sharia
to chase it.
You do the work, but you do not
violate your integrity to secure the outcome.
So it's about ethical boundary setting.
Yes.
The Islamic tradition uses a beautiful analogy to
clarify this exact balance.
The prophet described true reliance by pointing to
the birds.
They leave their nests in the morning hungry
and they return in the evening full.
The birds do not sit in the nest
expecting food to magically appear.
They fly, they search, they expend energy.
But they do so without the existential dread
that the earth will suddenly run out of
seeds.
They put in the effort without the anxiety
of trying to control the ultimate result.
Effort without anxiety.
That is the perfect distillation of the final
pivot.
Because after addressing his beloveds, his internal appetites,
his wealth, his status, his envy, his enemies,
and his sustenance, Hatim observes the absolute foundation
upon which people build their lives.
He sees that everyone places their trust in
something incredibly fragile.
Some trust their bank accounts.
Others trust their political connections.
And some trust their physical health.
And every single one of those foundations can
shatter in an instant.
So he finds the ultimate unshakable foundation in
the verse.
And if anyone puts his trust in Allah,
sufficient is Allah for him.
So Hatim adopts Tawakkul.
Yes, total unmitigated reliance on God after taking
the appropriate action.
He makes this the load-bearing architecture of
his entire existence.
That is a very heavy, profoundly quiet place
to land.
It really is.
So after Hatim finishes explaining these eight profound
reorientations, we return to the reaction of his
teacher.
Shekek, who initially wept with grief over the
seemingly paltry number of lessons his student had
learned.
What's fascinating here is the staggering theological claim
he issues in response to this.
It is astonishing.
He tells Hatim that he has personally examined
the Torah, the Gospel, the songs, and the
Holy Quran.
And he declares that all four of these
revealed books teach these exact same eight principles.
Whoever acts upon these eight, Shekek says, has
acted upon all the revealed scriptures.
It is a massive claim.
It is.
I urge you, the listener, to just sit
with that immense claim.
The gravity of that completely recontextualizes the entire
deep dive.
It does.
Shekek is stating that if you strip away
all the cultural noise, the centuries of complex
theological debate, and the endless volumes of commentary,
you find the exact same architectural core across
every major tradition.
Ghazali places this story in his letter to
tell his student that spiritual maturity is not
about an endless accumulation of knowledge.
No, it is about distilling your reality down
to a few fundamental questions.
Who do you love?
Who commands your desires?
Where is your wealth stored?
What is your metric for honor?
Who is your real enemy?
And what is holding you up?
Ghazali uses Hatim to demonstrate that 33 years
of study were not meant to produce a
walking encyclopedia.
They were meant to produce a transformed human
being.
At the beginning of the story, eight benefits
sounded like a catastrophic failure of education.
By the end of the story, you realize
that possessing these eight benefits is the definition
of mastering the curriculum of life.
We spend our entire lives assuming that growth
means adding complexity.
We gather more books, more opinions, more sophisticated
arguments, thinking that eventually the sheer volume of
information will save us.
But Hatim's 33 years suggests the exact opposite.
What if true spiritual education is actually a
process of aggressive subtraction?
What if the goal isn't to build a
more complicated mind, but to unlearn the noise
until you are left with nothing but the
few solid truths that can actually survive the
grave?
Which brings us to a final thought directed
squarely at you, the listener.
This deep dive began with a teacher asking
a student what he actually derived from 33
years of life and study.
If someone asked you today to name the
core pivots that currently define the architecture of
your life, would you have an answer?
And more importantly, if we apply Hatim's very
first test, would your answer actually survive the
grave?